Guide to the Mary Hallock Foote Papers, 1863-1924 (inclusive), 1868-1916 (bulk) M0115
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Mary Hallock Foote Papers
1863-1924
bulk
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Foote, Mary Hallock
M0115
6 Linear Feet
Correspondence with Helena Gilder, spanning their friendship of fifty years (1868-1916), and with other friends, family, and business associates. Also includes typed copy of Foote's work entitled, "Reminiscences".
Scope and Contents
The papers include correspondence, literary manuscripts, and artwork. The 613 letters to Helena De Kay Gilder, span a period of about fifty years (1868-1916). There are 65 letters from Foote to Richard Gilder, Helena's husband. There are also approximately 137 letters from Foote, her family, friends and business associates to each other, and finally, approximately 90 letters from Betty Foote Swift to her mother, Mary Hallock Foote, spanning the years 1911-1915.
The papers contain approximately 300 pages of the typescript for Foote's Reminiscences, 2 Foote manuscripts, and approximately 446 items of graphic material.
Biographical Note
Mary Hallock Foote was born Mary Haviland Hallock on November 19, 1847, at Milton-on-Hudson, N.Y., the youngest of four children. Her close-knit farming family were Quakers, Free-Soil Republicans of English stock, sympathetic to anti-slavery, temperance, and women's rights.
Nathaniel Hallock, Mary's father, unfortunately not an astute businessman in his farming practices, was keenly interested in literature and early influenced Mary in her admiration of Browning, Tennyson, Rossetti, and other Victorians.
Mary's mother, Ann Burling Hallock, affected Mary's development in the social graces. Charming and lady-like, she taught her children strict obedience, at the same time encouraging independence of thought and supporting Mary's decision to attend art school in New York City at the age of 17.
From 1860-64 Mary attended Poughkeepsie Female Seminary (later Vassar) and in Fall 1864 entered the Cooper School of Design for Women in NYC, the only institution at the time when anything approaching an art education could be had for a girl. There she met Helena de Kay, daughter of a prominent New York family and later wife of the distinguished poet and editor of Century Magazine, Richard Watson Gilder, beginning a life-long friendship and a transcontinental correspondence spanning 50 years.
New York teachers included Samuel Frost Johnson, with whom she studied color, John A.E. Whitney, Charles H. Burt, Wm. Rimmer, and Wm. J. Linton. Linton, a well-known English artist, was especially helpful to Foote, teaching her to draw directly on wood rather than on thin paper which then had to be placed face down onto a wood block, with the image transferred to the block by tracing on the paper from the reverse side. Under the tutelage of this exceptional teacher, Foote became one of the America's best designers on the wood.
Through Linton, she met A. V. S. Anthony, art editor for Tichnor and was commissioned in 1874 to work with Thomas Moran on works by Longfellow and Whittier. Quick to catch shadings of character and precise in her detailed representations, she was soon established as one of America's pre-eminent illustrators.
Because of her friendship with Helena de Kay at Cooper Union, she had met Helena's future husband, Richard Watson Gilder, the de facto editor of Scribner's Monthly, committed to securing the best artistic and literary talent in America for his magazine. He became the most important editor in her life, encouraging her to submit her illustrations to the magazine and, later, to write articles and stories accompanying them.
In 1873, Mary Hallock met Arthur De Wint Foote, son of a member of the Connecticut legislature. An engineering student at Yale's Sheffield Scientific School, he found that the best opportunities for engineers were opening up in the West, so he went west to work on the Southern Pacific system at Tehachapi Pass, then on the Sutro Tunnel in Virginia City, and finally the New Almaden quicksilver mine near San Jose where he became resident manager. He and Mary were married in Milton on February 9, 1876 but established their first home in the West at New Almaden. Their first child, Arthur Burling Foote was born there in April 1877.
Because of her husband's changing professional fortunes, Mary Hallock Foote moved with him from New Almaden to Santa Cruz, California, to Deadwood, Colorado, to Boise, Idaho, and finally to Grass Valley, California. When conditions made family residence impossible, Mary stayed with her family in Milton where her second child, Elizabeth Townsend Foote, was born in September 1882. A third child, Agnes, was born in Boise in June 1886.
Although she found material for her stories and illustrations wherever she was, it was the Leadville experience in 1879 that gave Foote some of the richest characterizations for her fiction. Stories based on the Leadville characters, especially her first novel, The Led-Horse Claim (1883), established Foote's reputation as a Western writer.
Recognized as one of America's best illustrators, she was chosen a juror on Chalk, Charcoal, Pastel and Other Drawings for the Chicago World's Fair Columbian Exposition in 1893. In 1894 she was elected to the National Academy of Women Painters and Sculptors and acclaimed as the "dean of women illustrators."
Because of her ability to examine the essence of Western life and the impact of specific locale on its residents, her work belongs to the late nineteenth century tradition known as "local color" and was accepted by Gilder and other editors as an important voice from the West.
In the last phase of their lives, Mary and Arthur returned to the East to live with their daughter Betty. Arthur died there, in Hingham, Massachusetts, in 1933. Mary Hallock Foote continued to reside in Hingham, dying on June 25, 1938.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Rosamond Gilder and Janet Micoleau, 1968. Some material purchased, 1977.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Note that material must be requested at least 36 hours in advance of intended use.
Women authors.; Mines and mineral resources -- History.; Women.; California -- History -- 1850-1950.; Authors.; American literature -- 20th century.; Illustrators.; Perry, Bliss; Savage, Ernest Albert; McMurray, George H. (George Harold); Wiley, A. J.; Ives, Halsey C.; Holden, Edward Singleton; Gilder, Richard Watson; Foote, Mary Hallock; New Almaden Mining Company; Gilder, Helena de Kay
- Correspondence, 1860-1984; Series 1
  Scope and Contents note
  Contains letters to or from Mary Hallock Foote.
  - Angus, M. Edith, 21 Apr. 1917-2 Feb. 1924 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Anthony, A.V.S., 18 Mar. 1874 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Bourn, Maud (Mrs. W.B.), [6 Oct. 1907] (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Dariall, Olive, 23 May 1899 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - de Kay, Charles, 8 July [1879]-14 Aug. [1881] (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - "Edith and Helen,", undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Family [unnamed], undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Foote, Arthur Burling, [25 Apr. 1933]-[10 Dec. 1934], and n.d. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Foote, Arthur De Wint, 30 Sept. 1873-13 Sept. 1893, and n.d. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Foote, Harry W., 28 Aug. 1933 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Fraser, W.G., 2 June 1890-10 June [1891?] (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Fry, Eliza T., 28 Apr. [1903] (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, [ca. 1860]-[ca. 1864] (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, [ca. 1864]-[ca. 1869] (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, 8 Feb. [1870]-[Sept. 1873] (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, [Sept. 1873]-[Jan.-Feb. 1874] (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, [Jan.-Feb. 1874]-[ca. 1874] (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, [Jan. 1875]-[30 Aug. 1875] (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, [Summer 1875]-[ca. 1875] (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, 14 Jan. [1876]-[June 1876] (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, 18 July [1876]-14 Sept. [1876] (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, 24 Sept. [1876]-7 Dec. [1876] (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, 21 [Dec. 1876]-[ca. 1876] (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, 16 Jan. [1877]-[May 1877] (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, [Spring 1877]-10 Dec. [1877] (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, 16 Dec. [1877]-[ca. 1877] (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, [ca. 1877] (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, 19 Jan. 1878-[ca. 1878] (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, [ca. 1878]-[ca. 1879] (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, [Jan. 1880]-[ca. 1880] (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, [ca. 1880]-[ca. 1881] (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, 2 Jan. 1882-[26 Aug. 1882] (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, [Sept. 1882]-19 May 1883 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, 25 May [1883]-30 Aug. 1884 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, 16 Dec. 1884-[ca. 1884] (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, [ca. 1884] (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, 5 Jan. 1885-22 Nov. [1885] (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, 13 Dec. [1885]-3 Aug. 1886 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, 1 Nov. 1886-[ca. 1886] (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, [ca. 1886] (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, [ca. 1886] (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, 9 Jan. 1887-10 Apr. 1887 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, 18 Apr. 1887-16 Nov. 1887 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, 6 Dec. 1887-[14 Feb. 1888] (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, [22 Feb. 1888]-28 Mar. 1888 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, 13 Apr. [1888]-22 Nov. 1888 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, 2 Dec. 1888-26 May 1889 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, 5 July 1889-14 Nov. 1889 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, 15 Dec. [1889]-2 Sept. [1890] (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, 10 Sept. 1890-[ca. 1890] (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, [24 Jan. 1891]-[July/Aug. 1891] (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, [Oct. 1891]-17 Jan. 1892 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, 15 Feb. 1892-11 Nov. 1892 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, [ca. 1892]-27 Mar. 1893 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, 30 Apr. 1893-22 July [1893] (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, 12 Aug. 1893-[ca. 1893] (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, 1 Jan. 1894-23 Mar. 1894 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, 27 Mar. [1894]-19 Oct. 1894 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, [2 Dec. 1894]-8 May 1895 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, 12 July 1895-[ca. 1895] (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, 22 Mar. [1896]-6 Dec. 1896 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, 25 Jan. 1897-29 May. 1897 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, 30 June 1897-22 Dec. 1897 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, 3 Jan. 1898-6 Mar. 1898 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, 18 Mar. [1898]-29 Dec. [1898] (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, [ca. 1898]-[16 Mar. 1899] (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, 3 Apr. 1899-[ca. 1899] (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, [ca. 1899]-27 Jan. 1901 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, 28 Apr. 1901-[ca. 1901] (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, [25 Mar. 1902]-15 Dec. 1902 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, 9 Jan. 1903-8 Nov. 1903 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, 10 Nov. 1903-10 Apr. [1904] (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, 18 May [1904]-8 Apr. [1905] (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, 7 July 1905-[ca. 1906] (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, [30 Mar. 1907]-[ca. 1907] (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, [Feb. 1908]-[ca. 1909] (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, 1 Jan. 1910-19 Jan. 1911 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, 7 Mar. [1911]-[ca. 1912] (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, [Apr. 1913]-29 Dec. [1913] (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, 27 Sept. [1914]-7 Jan. 1915 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, 27 Jan. 1915-25 Oct. 1915 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, [5 Nov. 1915]-[ca. 1932- ] (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, undated (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Gilder, Richard, 10 Aug. (Box 4, Folder 14)
    1872-26 Oct. [1877]
  - Gilder, Richard, 15 Jan. (Box 4, Folder 15)
    1878-3 Nov. [1887]
  - Gilder, Richard, 3 Feb. [1888]-[14 June 1901] (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Gilder, Richard, n.y., 7 Feb.-25 Sept. (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Gilder, Richard, n.d. (1) (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Gilder, Richard, n.d. (2) (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Gilder, Rodman, Summer, 1878 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Hallock, Ann, 17 June 1879-4 July 1889, and n.d. (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Hallock, Philadelphia, 187- (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Houghton Mifflin and Company, 9 Feb. 1900-31 July 1917 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Ives, Halsey, 20 Dec. 1892 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Nicholas, Edith, 1 Oct. 1891 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Perry, Bliss, 5 Dec. 1901-16 June 1904 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Root, Fred S., 9 Nov. 1899 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Savage, Albert C., 6 Feb. 1887 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Sherman, Elizabeth Hallock, 2 Jan. 1912, and n.d. (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Sherman, Jack, 9 Feb 1863 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Soulsby, Lucy, 6 Jan. 1921 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Swift, Betty Foote, 10 Dec. 1900-[18 Feb. 1911] (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Swift, Betty Foote, [23 Feb. 1911]-[28 Aug. 1911] (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Swift, Betty Foote, [1 Sept. 1911]-[14 Mar. 1912] (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Swift, Betty Foote, [21 Mar. 1912]-[12 June 1912] (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Swift, Betty Foote, [26 July 1912]-[10 Dec. 1912] (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Swift, Betty Foote, [19 Dec. 1912]-[19 Apr. 1913] (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Swift, Betty Foote, [19 Apr. 1913]-[6 July 1913] (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Swift, Betty Foote, [19 July 1913]-[30 Sept. 1913] (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Swift, Betty Foote, [12 Oct. 1913]-[20 Sept. 1924] (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Swift, Betty Foote, undated (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Walter, Emma, 19 Apr. 1903 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Wolle, Francis, 8 July 1929 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Yoshida, M., 27 Sept. 1898 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Unknown, 17 Oct. 1901 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Angus, M. Edith, 21 Apr. 1917-2 Feb. 1924 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Anthony, A.V.S., 18 Mar. 1874 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Bourn, Maud (Mrs. W.B.), [6 Oct. 1907] (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Dariall, Olive, 23 May 1899 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - de Kay, Charles, 8 July [1879]-14 Aug. [1881] (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - "Edith and Helen,", undated (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Family [unnamed], undated (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Foote, Arthur Burling, [25 Apr. 1933]-[10 Dec. 1934], and n.d. (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Foote, Arthur De Wint, 30 Sept. 1873-13 Sept. 1893, and n.d. (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Foote, Harry W., 28 Aug. 1933 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Fraser, W.G., 12 June 1890-10 June [1891?] (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Fry, Eliza T., 28 Apr. [1903] (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, [ca.1860]-[ca. 1864] (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, [ca. 1864]-[ca. 1869] (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, 8 Feb. [1870]-[Sept. 1873] (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, [Sept. 1873]-[Jan.-Feb. 1874] (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, [Jan.-Feb. 1874]-[ca. 1874] (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, [Jan. 1875]-[30 Aug. 1875] (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, [Summer 1875]-[ca. 1875] (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, 14 Jan. [1876]-[June 1876] (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, 18 July [1876]-14 Sept. [1876] (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, 24 Sept. [1876]-7 Dec. [1876] (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, 21 [Dec. 1876]-[ca. 1876] (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, 16 Jan. [1877]-[May 1877] (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, [Spring 1877]-10 Dec. [1877] (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, 16 Dec. [1877]-[ca. 1877] (Box 6, Folder 26)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, [ca. 1877] (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, 19 Jan. 1878-[ca. 1878] (Box 6, Folder 28)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, [ca. 1878]-[ca. 1879] (Box 6, Folder 29)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, [Jan. 1880]-[ca. 1880] (Box 6, Folder 30)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, [ca. 1880]-[ca. 1881] (Box 6, Folder 31)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, 2 Jan. 1882-[26 Aug. 1882] (Box 6, Folder 32)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, [Sept. 1882]-19 May 1883 (Box 6, Folder 33)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, 25 May [1883]-30 Aug. 1884 (Box 6, Folder 34)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, 16 Dec. 1884-[ca. 1884] (Box 6, Folder 35)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, [ca. 1884] (Box 6, Folder 36)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, 5 Jan. 1885-22 Nov. [1885] (Box 6, Folder 37)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, 13 Dec. [1885]-3 Aug. 1886 (Box 6, Folder 38)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, 1 Nov. 1886-[ca. 1886] (Box 6, Folder 39)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, [ca. 1886] (Box 6, Folder 40)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, [ca. 1886] (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, 9 Jan. 1887-10 Apr. 1887 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, 18 Apr. 1887-16 Nov. 1887 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, 6 Dec. 1887-[14 Feb.1888] (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, [22 Feb. 1888]-28 Mar. 1888 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, 13 Apr. [1888]-22 Nov. 1888 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - 2 Dec. 1888-26 May 1889 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, 5 July 1889-14 Nov. 1889 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, 15 Dec. [1889]-2 Sept. [1890] (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, 10 Sept. 1890-[ca. 1890] (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, [24 Jan. 1891]-[July/Aug. 1891] (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, [Oct. 1891]-17 Jan. 1892 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, 15 Feb. 1892-11 Nov. 1892 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, [ca. 1892]-27 Mar. 1893 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, 30 Apr. 1893-22 July [1893] (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, 2 Aug. 1893-[ca. 1893] (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, 1 Jan. 1894-23 Mar. 1894 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, 27 Mar. [1894]-19 Oct. 1894 (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, [2 Dec. 1894]-8 May 1895 (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, 12 July 1895-[ca. 1895] (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, 22 Mar. [1896]-6 Dec. 1896 (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, 25 Jan. 1897-29 May. 1897 (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, 30 June 1897-22 Dec. 1897 (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, 3 Jan. 1898-6 Mar. 1898 (Box 7, Folder 24)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, 8 Mar. [1898]-29 Dec. [1898] (Box 7, Folder 25)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, [ca. 1898]-[16 Mar. 1899] (Box 7, Folder 26)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, 3 Apr. 1899-[ca. 1899] (Box 7, Folder 27)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, [ca. 1899]-27 Jan. 1901 (Box 7, Folder 28)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, 28 Apr. 1901-[ca. 1901] (Box 7, Folder 29)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, [25 Mar. 1902]-15 Dec. 1902 (Box 7, Folder 30)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, 9 Jan. 1903-8 Nov. 1903 (Box 7, Folder 31)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, 10 Nov. 1903-10 Apr. [1904] (Box 7, Folder 32)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, 18 May [1904]-8 Apr. [1905] (Box 7, Folder 33)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, 7 July 1905-[ca. 1906] (Box 7, Folder 34)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, [30 Mar. 1907]-[ca. 1907] out (Box 7, Folder 35)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, [Feb. 1908]-[ca. 1909] (Box 7, Folder 36)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, 1 Jan. 1910-19 Jan. 1911 (Box 7, Folder 37)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, 7 Mar. [1911]-[ca. 1912] (Box 7, Folder 38)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, [Apr. 1913]-29 Dec. [1913] (Box 7, Folder 39)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, 27 Sept. [1914]-7 Jan. 1915 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, 27 Jan. 1915-25 Oct. 1915 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, [5 Nov. 1915]-[ca. 1932- ] (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, undated (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Gilder, Richard, 10 Aug. 1872-26 Oct. [1877] (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, 15 Jan. 1878-3 Nov. [1887] (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, 3 Feb. [1888]-[14 June 1901] (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, n.y., 7 Feb.-25 Sept. (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, n.d. (1) (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, n.d. (2) (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Gilder, Rodman, Summer, 1878 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Hallock, Ann, 17 June 1879-4 July 1889, and n.d. (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Hallock, Philadelphia, 187- (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Houghton Mifflin and Company, 9 Feb. 1900-31 July 1917 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Ives, Halsey, 20 Dec. 1892 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Nicholas, Edith, 1 Oct. 1891 (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Perry, Bliss, 5 Dec. 1901-16 June 1904 (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Root, Fred S., 29 Nov. 1899 (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Savage, Albert C., 6 Feb. 1887 (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - Sherman, Elizabeth Hallock, 2 Jan. 1912, and n.d. (Box 8, Folder 20)
  - Sherman, Jack, 9 Feb 1863 (Box 8, Folder 21)
  - Soulsby, Lucy, 6 Jan. 1921 (Box 8, Folder 22)
  - Swift, Betty Foote, 10 Dec. 1900-[18 Feb. 1911] (Box 8, Folder 23)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, [23 Feb. 1911]-[28 Aug. 1911] (Box 8, Folder 24)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, [1 Sept. 1911]-[14 Mar. 1912] (Box 8, Folder 25)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, [21 Mar. 1912]-[12 June 1912] (Box 8, Folder 26)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, [26 July 1912]-[10 Dec. 1912] (Box 8, Folder 27)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, [19 Dec. 1912]-[19 Apr. 1913] (Box 8, Folder 28)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, [19 Apr. 1913]-[6 July 1913] (Box 8, Folder 29)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, [19 July 1913]-[30 Sept. 1913] (Box 8, Folder 30)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, [12 Oct. 1913]-[20 Sept. 1924] (Box 8, Folder 31)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, undated (Box 8, Folder 32)
  - Walter, Emma, 19 Apr. 1903 (Box 8, Folder 33)
  - Wolle, Francis, 8 July 1929 (Box 8, Folder 34)
  - Yoshida, M., 27 Sept. 1898 (Box 8, Folder 35)
  - Unknown, 17 Oct. 1901 (Box 8, Folder 36)
- Correspondence, 1885-1945; Series 2
  Contains letters which refer to Mary Hallock Foote but no materials written by or to her.
  [Incoming to those listed first]
  - Chapel, E.O, (Grass Valley Chamber of Commerce), 24 Nov. 1926 (Box 8, Folder 37)
  - Delessert, M., 6 July 1899 (Box 8, Folder 38)
  - Foote, Arthur Burling, 15 Mar. 1904-4 May 1945 (Box 8, Folder 39)
  - Foote, Arthur de Wint, Arnold, Louise-Foote, Nathaniel (Box 8, Folder 40)
  - Foote, Gilder, Richard and Helena-J[enkins], Edward (Box 8, Folder 41)
  - Foote, J[enkins],Elizabeth, 4 Nov. 1919-30 Mar. 1929, and n.d. (Box 8, Folder 42)
  - Foote, Lyon, Sung-Yi, S.K. (Box 8, Folder 43)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, Anthony, A.V.S.-unknown (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Gilder, Rodman, 7 Sept. 1938 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Hallock, Ann, 5 Nov.-4 Dec. 1885 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Hallock, Anna Walter, 2 June, n.y. (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Hallock, Sarah Walter, 2 Jan. 1886-2 Sept. 1890 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Sherman, Elizabeth, 9 May 1877-10 Apr. 1890 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Swift, Betty Foote, Angus, M. Edith-Jenkins, Elizabeth (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Delessert, M., 6 July 1899 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Foote, Arthur Burling, 15 Mar. 1904-4 May 1945 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Foote, Arthur de Wint, Arnold, Louise-Foote, Nathaniel (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Foote, Gilder, Richard and Helena-J[enkins], Edward (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Foote, Lyon, Sung-Yi, S.K. (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Gilder, Helena de Kay, Anthony, A.V.S.-unknown (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Gilder, Rodman, 7 Sept. 1938 (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Hallock, Ann, 5 Nov.-4 Dec. 1885 (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Hallock, Anna Walter, 2 June, n.y. (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Hallock, Sarah Walter, 2 Jan. 1886-2 Sept. 1890 (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - Sherman, Elizabeth, 9 May 1877-10 Apr. 1890 (Box 9, Folder 18)